A Guide to the Mary Eveyln Victoria Papers, 1931-1963
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Papers of Mary Evelyn Victoria Hunter, 1931-1963
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1962-44
12 items
Writings reports, and biography of Mrs. Mary Evelyn Victoria Hunter, the founder of the School of Home Economics at Virginia State University.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mary Evelyn Victoria Hunter recieved the Bachelor of Science Degree from Prairie View A & M College and was the first African American female upon whom the Master's Degree was conferred at Iowa State University where she also completed course requirements of the doctorate degree. Texas College confers upon her the honorary degree of Doctor of Law.
While in Texas, Dr. Hunter was a member of the State Federation's of Women's Clubs, the State Interracial Commission, and the board of Directors of the Texas Home for Delinquent Girls. She devised a plan for purchasing county recreation parks in various sections of Texas and organized the annual "Home Economics Week" on a State-wide basis.
In 1953, she was the recipient of the Alumni Award for outstanding achievement in school, community, and home relations at Prairie View A & M College. Her intrest in adult education resulted in her sponsering the Chesterfield County. Research Project which resulted in a extended program of adult education. Dr. Hunter has contributed articles to the Virginia State College Gazette, Journal of Negro Education, Bulletin of the Confrence of Presidents of Negro Land-Grant Colleges, the Journal of Home Economics, the Service Service Review and the Agricultural Digest.
Mary E.V. Hunter came to Virginia State College in 1931, to become Head of the Department and Professor of Home Economics. Dr.Hunter served in this department until she retired in 1955.
Scope and Content Information
Writings on a number of isssues make up Mrs. Hunter's papers. Most of the articles address some aspect of the socio-economic conditions of the African American family during the era of segregation in Virginia. How did members of the academic community attempt to impact on the society through self help projects, and other innovative means to close the gap.
Contents List
- Literary
  - Development of the School of Home Economics 1931-1955 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Steps in Making a Chair from a Barrel 1935 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Special course in Nutrition, Development of Home Economics and Teaching Home Economics For home Making 1942, 1949, 1928-1953 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Program of the Chesterfield County Field Laboatory 1944-1948 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - The Past, the Present, and the Future outlook of Farm Famalies, Adult Education Handbook, and a suggested Program for Citizen Participation in Public School Education Virginia State College. 1950 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Fifty Tested Recipes on the Use of the White Potato 1954 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Admission of Student to American Colleges and Universities 1955 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Suggested Program for Farm Famalies 1955 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - What the Negro should do for the Next Fifty Years 1955 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Responsibility Must be Taught in the Schools n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)